PROFESSOR: OK, so we've just found out
ways to upgrade our planning agents
with heuristics.
Now we got to figure out how
to do it in practice.
Not just, how does the math work, but
given a problem, how do I give my
agent this heuristic upgrade?
Most of the work involved in solving
hard search problems is actually
coming up with a heuristic
in the first place.
So for the example of Romania here, the
admissible heuristics come from
what are called relaxed problems.
What's a relaxed problem?
What it means is we take our original
problem, which is hard, and it's
difficult to compute how far we
actually are from the goal.
And we change the problem in such a way
that we have only made things the
same or easier.
The idea is in this new problem it's
easy to find cost to the goal.
They'll just be cheaper because
we've made the problem easier.
For example, if we imagined in Romania,
in addition to the roads we
actually have, we've also got a straight
line road straight to the
solution, in this case Bucharest.
Well, that would be an easier problem.
It can't take any longer with the
presence of these new roads.
And in this new problem, we don't
even have to run search.
We just know you always
take the direct road.
It's kind of a convoluted way to come
up with the straight line distance,
but it illustrates this idea that by
taking our problem and making it
easier we get lower bounds on the
costs in the harder problem.
Here's another case that
you've already seen.
Manhattan distance for
the Pac-Man problem.
What is the relaxation here?
We say, well, I don't know how far I am
from the goal given all those walls
and the going back and forth.
But if I could change the problem so
that Pac-Man could walk through walls,
well, it's easy to figure
out the quickest way.
You just go straight there.
And so that's a relaxation of the
problem, which essentially involves
adding new operators.
But, in general, though you can then
solve this new problem with search, in
general, you add operators such that you
know the solution more or less in
closed form.
Sometimes, we actually use
inadmissible heuristics.
So if you come up with a heuristic and
it works really well in practice, and
you discover every now and then it
over estimates, well you have no
guarantee of optimality.
You also don't have a guarantee
of sub optimality.
And for many problems a little bit sub
optimal sometimes is worth a huge
increase in speed.
And sometimes, a little bit of
inadmissibility, not in and of itself,
but because it lets you be more
aggressive with heuristic, is
sometimes worth it.
But for now, we're going to worry about
creating admissible heuristics.
So we're going to talk through an
example where we can come up with
multiple heuristics.
It's the example of the eight puzzle.
So here's the eight puzzle.
You start with a puzzle, like what's in
the upper left in some start state.
Your actions are you can move a square
with a number in it into the blank
square if its adjacent.
So what the robot's doing here, you
can move the eight rightward if
there's no other tile right.
The goal is to end up in this
configuration, where the
numbers are in order.
How many of you have played
with an eight puzzle?
Yeah, did you like it?
These things were a hit once.
This is like the Xbox 100 years ago.
We have a search problem.
We have states.
They're configurations of numbers.
In fact, they're kind of a list of
numbers, so it's a permutation.
How many of them are there?
We could do some combinatorics.
It's going to be the number of these
factorials, so it's a lot of states.
What are the actions?
Well, the actions are any of
the adjacent squares to the
blank can be moved.
What are the successors?
Well, you compute the appropriate
permutation.
What's the branching factor like?
For example, from the start state here
how many successors do I have?
Well, I can move this one.
I can move this one.
I've got four successor
from the start state.
So it's not a huge branching factor, but
it's going to be a pretty big tree
before it's all done.
What's should our costs be?
Well.
Maybe it's more expensive to move
the eight, but probably not.
So let's say the costs are all one.
So in that case, we're just trying to
find a solution of minimum cost, which
means of fewest steps.
So we've got our search problem.
And we can point at a breadth
first search.
And breadth first search
we'll truck away.
We can point at Uniform Cost Search.
And Uniform Cost Search
we'll truck away.
Because the costs are one, they'll
do more or less the same thing.
We want a heuristic, so we
can do things faster.
So here's one heuristic.
Let's count up the number
of tiles that are not in
their destination position.
Is this a heuristic?
Does it take a state and
return a real number?
Sure.
What real number does it return?
Well, we can look at the start state
here, and we can say, well, this one
is out of position.
And this one's out of position.
And they're actually all
out of position.
So this one's going to return eight.
Why is that admissible?
Why is it the case that I can't possibly
be closer than eight steps?
Why can't I come up with some genius
brilliant eight puzzle move that gets
them all in order in one step?
The answer is it's not how
the eight puzzle works.
You move one tile at a time.
And when you move that tile, it
either goes into its final
position or it doesn't.
There's no move that can fix two squares
at once, assuming we treat the
blank appropriately.
And so it's admissible because every
move in the optimal solution either
fixes one of these mistakes,
or doesn't, but it can't
fix more than one.
So the heuristic of the
start is eight.
We might in fact be 15 away at the
start, but we're not more than eight.
So there's an admissible heuristic.
Does it work?
Well, how much work we do is going to
depend actually on how deep the
optimal path is in the tree.
If this thing's really scrambled,
we have to go deep into the
tree to find the path.
If it's not very scrambled, then lots of
search techniques are going to work
reasonably well.
So Uniform Cost Search versus this
misplaced tiles heuristic is shown.
And you can see that at the beginning
the differences isn't so great, but as
we get deeper into the tree in order
to find our optimal path, this tree
grows exponentially.
And so you can see that Uniform Cost
Search just does not keep up with A
star using even this simple heuristic.
Only 227 versus 3 times
10 to the sixth.
This is a relaxed problem heuristic.
It is the exact solution, so eight is
the exact cost of the exact solution
to an easier version of
the eight puzzle.
What is the easier version of the eight
puzzle that you can actually
solve in eight steps?
Well, if you could remove the pieces.
If you could, in every step, take some
piece and put in the right place, that
can't make this problem
be any more expensive.
And we know how long it's
going to be to solve it.
We know it's going to
take eight steps.
So here's an extreme relaxation
of the problem.
It gives rise to an admissible
heuristic.
But it's a very loose heuristic.
It's an extreme relaxation.
We're probably a lot
farther than eight.
Can we come up with a
better heuristic?
Well, maybe.
What if we had an easier version of
the eight puzzle, not so easy that
you've ripped it apart and you
can fix each one in one step.
But what if each tile was
simply independent.
It was a vertical puzzle.
They were all on their own track and
they could slide past each other.
This would be easier because we would
have all the moves we currently have
that are legal, plus some more
that involve sliding tiles
on top of each other.
And in this case, how far am I?
In this case, all of the
tiles are independent.
So how hard is it to get the one into
position in this easier problem?
I can't do it in one step.
How much is it going to take?
One to the left, two up,
it's three away.
And so what I could do is I
could basically add up all
the Manhattan distances.
Now that doesn't actually solve
the real problem for me, but
it's a lower bounds.
And it's probably better
than the previous one.
So let's take a look.
This is the total Manhattan distance.
We know why it's admissible.
Actually, there's two ways you
can show it's admissible.
This is worth pointing out.
One is by illustrating the relaxed
problem, like I did.
And then arguing that it is, in
fact, a strict relaxation.
And the other way is just from first
principle saying, well, here's why you
can't possibly do any
better than that.
And you always have these two routes,
direct proof or construction of a
relaxation.
So we already computed would
the h to the start is.
And it turns out to be 18.
That's a lot better than eight.
It tells us, in fact, we weren't
even so close as eight.
We're at least 18 away, and probably
further than that.
Is it better?
For shallow problems, its actually
not much better.
But by the time you get to deeper
problems, it's substantially better
than the tiles heuristic.
And this illustrates a general point
that as your heuristic gets tighter,
as it gets closer to the true
cost, you do less work.
And that's actually a deep
fact about A star.
As the heuristic gets closer to the
true cost, you'll do less work.
Forget all these relaxed problems.
I have a heuristic for you.
We're going to look at a state and we're
going to actually figure out how
far we are from the solution.
It's possible.
We have a search problem,
we can find this number.
Is that a heuristic?
Yes.
Would it be admissible?
Yes, trivially admissible.
Would we save on the number of nodes
we expanded in the search?
Yeah, you basically go straight
down optimal paths only.
OK, so, why did I tell you about
these other heuristics?
What's wrong with using the actual
cost as a heuristic?
It looks great.
It's kind of expensive to compute.
So even though you don't expand many
nodes, each one launches a search
problem that's as hard as the thing
you were trying to speed up in the
first place.
So with A star there's
this general point.
In general, there's a trade off between
the quality of your estimate,
the tightness of your heuristic,
and the amount of work you
have to do per node.
And the way that looks like is better
heuristics mean you expand fewer nodes
because they tend to be tighter.
On the other hand, each node is
expensive because you have to do the
extra work to compute the
heuristic itself.
You'll see this in your project ones.
As your heuristics are sufficiently
good, you may actually see slowdowns
in your wall clock time.
So basically, there's going to
be a family of heuristics.
Some of them are really bad.
That just always tell
you you're there.
And some of them are really good.
They know exactly what you should do.
And some of them are in between.
And usually the sweet
spot is in between.
You don't want your heuristic
to be clueless, but fast.
Because then you're basically
not exploiting A star.
You don't want it to be so good that
it's solving the problem because then
probably you're wasting your time.
And somewhere in between is
usually a good balance.